<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on The Bored Octopus</title>
    <link>https://soroush.github.io/en/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on The Bored Octopus</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://soroush.github.io/en/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>PIMPL idiom in C&#43;&#43;</title>
      <link>https://soroush.github.io/en/2020/08/13/pimpl-idiom-in-cpp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://soroush.github.io/en/2020/08/13/pimpl-idiom-in-cpp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Developers working on a &amp;ldquo;software library&amp;rdquo; in C++ (or any other&#xA;native language) should follow a set of critically important rules, or&#xA;their customers will soon be in trouble using their product. Some of&#xA;these rules are for example&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://semver.org/&#34;&gt;Semantic Versioning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Good API Design&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;and &lt;strong&gt;Keeping Backward Compatibility&lt;/strong&gt;. The later one has many aspects&#xA;and requires its detailed post. In this post, I will discuss one of&#xA;the vastly used techniques in C++ which helps developers to keep&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;Backward Compatibility&lt;/strong&gt; in binary (ABI) level.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pure Functions in C&#43;&#43;‬</title>
      <link>https://soroush.github.io/en/2020/08/06/pure-functions-in-cpp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://soroush.github.io/en/2020/08/06/pure-functions-in-cpp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the best optimisation features of C++ is declaring functions as &lt;strong&gt;pure&lt;/strong&gt;.&#xA;This one is less known to developers, though it can be an excellent optimisation&#xA;hit for your software. Marking a function with “pure” attribute enables a wide&#xA;range of possible optimisations for the compiler. You must declare your pure&#xA;functions as such, in all code that cares about performance. In this post, I am&#xA;going to show how to use this feature and its effects on generated code.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>English Blog!</title>
      <link>https://soroush.github.io/en/2020/08/05/translating-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://soroush.github.io/en/2020/08/05/translating-blog/</guid>
      <description>So I started to translate my old Persian content into English, as an exercise (well, mostly out of bordem duo to COVID-19 lockdown&amp;hellip;). I&amp;rsquo;ll keep dates intact. I hope you&amp;rsquo;ll find it interesting&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Gregorian Calendar Systems in Qt</title>
      <link>https://soroush.github.io/en/2020/08/02/persian-calendar-in-qt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://soroush.github.io/en/2020/08/02/persian-calendar-in-qt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For Iranian general public, working with date and time in a computer system has always&#xA;been challenging. As opposed to - almost - entire population of the planet, we use a&#xA;different calendar system (actually a better one!) but computer systems are not&#xA;designed and developed with non-Gregorian calendaring in mind. So we always have&#xA;to use unconventional methods and hacks to provide functionality of&#xA;the official calendar of the country - Solar Hijri&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Personally, for me the absence of the Solar Hijri calendar in Qt has always&#xA;been annoying. Whenever I wanted to work with date and time in my C++ GUI&#xA;applications, I had two options: Either use my own custom widgets (which where&#xA;not as good as Qt&amp;rsquo;s widgets), or simply use the Gregorian calendar (which is&#xA;annoying for the final user).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Since version 4.6, right after I released Persian translation of Qt, I was&#xA;thinking of implementing the solar calendar for this&#xA;framework. Unfortunately, in that time it was not possible to implement it for&#xA;many reasons. However, I made some prototypes, but it did not make it to Qt5.&#xA;Qt5 had its own sad story, with the premature release of version 5.0; the&#xA;opportunity created by changing the major version was also missed.&#xA;Though finally, after 6 years and forgetting all about calendars, I had the&#xA;chance to implement the solar Hijri calendar for Qt 5.10. The final version has been&#xA;released with Qt 5.14 on December 12, 2019. This post describes challenges, and&#xA;the process of the work, and also the API itself.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://soroush.github.io/en/en/static/images/jalali.gif&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Running Example&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mathematical Constants in C&#43;&#43;</title>
      <link>https://soroush.github.io/en/2018/04/13/math-constants-in-cpp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://soroush.github.io/en/2018/04/13/math-constants-in-cpp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;None of C++ standards has defined π number. So every programmer who needs to do&#xA;some math including, for example, trigonomerty or statistics, has to define π&#xA;herself. Luckily header files have defined π (See &lt;code&gt;M_PI&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;math.h&lt;/code&gt;). Though it&#xA;is not ultimately safe and portable to use these constants. It might casue&#xA;numeric errors in critical applications. In this blog post, I am going to show a&#xA;better way to reach a safe π.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Worst Ever Qt Bug (for me!)</title>
      <link>https://soroush.github.io/en/2017/05/09/worst-ever-bug/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://soroush.github.io/en/2017/05/09/worst-ever-bug/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I think Qt is one of the best software development frameworks. It has a nice GUI&#xA;library alongside with many other tools, provided as a neat and clean API. KDE&#xA;desktop environment is almost entirely based on Qt framework. I&amp;rsquo;ve been using it&#xA;for a decade now, and I have successfully delivered dozens of projects &amp;ndash; both&#xA;embedded and desktop &amp;ndash; most of them only using Qt. Though starting from version&#xA;5.3, a tiny bug has appeared in the core library, that makes life difficult for&#xA;me: It is impossible to insert invisible characters in Qt&amp;rsquo;s text engine. That is&#xA;you can&amp;rsquo;t type ZWNJ, ZWJ, LRE, RLE and PDF characters. (I have described what&#xA;they in this post:&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Control Charachters and Bi-Directional Text&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;The effect of this bug is so huge that makes it impossible for me to use KDE or&#xA;any other application that uses Qt. To see how it didn&amp;rsquo;t work for us, imagine&#xA;being unable to type, for example, &amp;ldquo;space&amp;rdquo; character in any application on your&#xA;operating system! In this post I am going to show a workaround and explain how&#xA;to fix this bug. It is already fixed in recent versions of Qt, though it is not&#xA;in official repositories yet. Fortunately, the workaround is very simple and&#xA;does not break anything. Finally I&amp;rsquo;ll provide a patch for 5.9. Hope this helps&#xA;someone.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
