<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>qt,c&#43;&#43;,bug on The Bored Octopus</title>
    <link>https://soroush.github.io/en/categories/qtc&#43;&#43;bug/</link>
    <description>Recent content in qt,c&#43;&#43;,bug on The Bored Octopus</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://soroush.github.io/en/categories/qtc++bug/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Worst Ever Qt Bug (for me!)</title>
      <link>https://soroush.github.io/en/2017/05/09/worst-ever-bug/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://soroush.github.io/en/2017/05/09/worst-ever-bug/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I think Qt is one of the best software development frameworks. It has a nice GUI
library alongside with many other tools, provided as a neat and clean API. KDE
desktop environment is almost entirely based on Qt framework. I&amp;rsquo;ve been using it
for a decade now, and I have successfully delivered dozens of projects &amp;ndash; both
embedded and desktop &amp;ndash; most of them only using Qt. Though starting from version
5.3, a tiny bug has appeared in the core library, that makes life difficult for
me: It is impossible to insert invisible characters in Qt&amp;rsquo;s text engine. That is
you can&amp;rsquo;t type ZWNJ, ZWJ, LRE, RLE and PDF characters. (I have described what
they in this post:
&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Control Charachters and Bi-Directional Text&lt;/a&gt;.
The effect of this bug is so huge that makes it impossible for me to use KDE or
any other application that uses Qt. To see how it didn&amp;rsquo;t work for us, imagine
being unable to type, for example, &amp;ldquo;space&amp;rdquo; character in any application on your
operating system! In this post I am going to show a workaround and explain how
to fix this bug. It is already fixed in recent versions of Qt, though it is not
in official repositories yet. Fortunately, the workaround is very simple and
does not break anything. Finally I&amp;rsquo;ll provide a patch for 5.9. Hope this helps
someone.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>